本节 我们将对学习一次一密的攻击
In this segment, we're gonna look at
attacks on the one time pad, and some
和使用流密码时所需要注意的一些事情 但在开始前
things you need to be careful with when
you use the stream cipher. But before we
我们对讲过的知识进行快速的回顾 回想下一次
do that, let's do a quick review of where
we were. So recall that the one time
pad encrypts messages by XORing the
message and a secret key, where the secret
一密是通过将明文与密钥异或来加密的，这里密钥
key is as long as the message. Similarly,
decryption is done by similarly
和明文一样长 类似的 解密同样是
XORing the cipher text, and the same
secret key. When the key is uniform and
通过密文与相同密钥之间的异或来实现的 当密钥是均匀、
random, we prove that the one-time pad has
this information theoretic security that
随机的时 我们证明一次一密具有理论上的信息安全性
Shannon called perfect secrecy. A problem
was, of course, the keys are as long as
也就是香农称作的完善保密 显然有个问题是密钥与明文一样长
the message, so the one-time pad is very
difficult to use. We then talked about a
所以一次一密很难使用 之后我们讨论了
way to make the one time pad practical by
using a pseudo random generator that
通过使用伪随机数发生器使一次一密实用化
伪随机数生成器可以将一个短的种子信息扩展成一条更长的信息。 流密码的工作方法
expands a short seed into a much larger
message and the way a stream cypher
本质上是使用伪随机数发生器  与一次一密的方法一样。
worked, essentially using a pseudo random
generator, was in the same way as the one
基本上 流密码中我们不使用真随机序列 而使用
time pad, basically, but rather than using a
truly random pad, we used this pseudo
伪随机序列 这个序列是由发生器输入的短密钥扩展而成 并与明文一样长
random pad that's expanded to be as long
as the message from the short key that's
所以这里我们说它的安全性不再依赖于
given as input to the generator. We said
now the security no longer relies on
完善保密 因为（实用的）流密码不可能是完善保密的 而
perfect secrecy because stream ciphers
cannot be perfectly secure. Instead
依赖于伪随机数发生器的性质
security relies on properties of the
pseudo random generator and we said that
我们说伪随机发生器必须是不可预测的 但事实上
the pseudo random generator essentially
needs to be unpredictable, but in fact it
证明这个定义使用起来有点困难 这里我们将了解一个
turns out that definition is a little bit
hard to work with and we're going to see a
关于PRG（伪随机数生成器）的安全性的更好的定义 大概会花两节的内容。但本节
better definition of security for PRGs in
about two segments. But in this segment
我们将讨论对一次一密的攻击 第一个我想讨论的攻击
we're going to talk about attacks on the
one time pad. And the first attack I want to
是“二次密码本攻击”  所以记住
talk about is what's called the two time pad
attack, okay? so remember that the
一次一密之所以叫“一次性”密码本是因为密码本只能用来加密
one time pad is called "one time" pad because
the pad can only be used to encrypt a
单个信息 这里我想展示的是 如果同样的密码本为不止一个明文加密时
single message. I want to show you that if
the same pad is used to encrypt more than
安全性也就不复存在了 而且窃听者可以完全
one message, then security goes out the
window, and basically an eavesdropper can
解密加密消息 那么我们来看一个例子
completely decrypt encrypted messages.
So let's look at an example. So here we
这里有两个使用相同密码本加密的明文消息，m1和m2
have two messages m1 and m2 that are
encrypted using the same pad. So the
得到的密文c1和c2 分别是m1和m2的加密
resulting ciphertext, C1 and C2, again
basically are encryptions of these
但加密时使用的是相同密码本 现假设
messages, m1 and m2, but both are
encrypted using the same pad. Now suppose
窃听者在截取了c1和c2 并且截获到了 他就有了c1和c2
an eavesdropper intercepts C1 and C2, and
he obtains, he basically has both C1 and C2.
窃听者就会很自然的去计算出c1和c2的异或
The natural thing for the eavesdropper
to do is actually compute the XOR of C1
当他计算异或后他会得到什么呢？我希望每个人都能想到
and C2 and what does he get when he
computes this XOR? So I hope everybody
基本上 当你将c1和c2异或 密钥就会被抵消
sees that, basically, once you XOR
C1 and C2, the pads cancel out, and
essentially, what comes out of this is the
XOR of the plaintext messages.
本质上得到的就是两段明文的异或。
And it turns out that English basically
has enough redundancy, such that if I give
英语实际上有着足够的冗余 因此如果我给
you the XOR of two plaintext
messages, you can actually recover those
你两个明文的异或，你能完全还原出
two mesages completely. More importantly
for us is these messages are encoded
两个明文消息 对我们来说更重要的是这些信息使用了
using ASCII. In fact, ASCII encodings has
enough redundancy, such that given the
ASCII码编码 事实上，ASCII本身就有足够的冗余 因此 给定
XOR of two ASCII encoded messages,
you can recover the original messages
两个ASCII码信息的异或，你可以还原出原消息
back. So, essentially, given these XORs,
you can recover both messages. So the
所以，本质上，给定这些异或，可以还原出两条明文消息
thing to remember here is if you ever use
the same pad to encrypt multiple messages
所以要记住的是  如果你使用同样的密钥序列去加密多条信息
an attack who intercepts the resulting
ciphertexts can eventually recover the
截取密文的攻击者最终可以
existing plaintexts without too much
work. So, the stream cipher key or the
毫不费力地还原出明文 所以，流密码的密钥或者
one time pad key should never ever, ever,
ever be used more than once. So, let's
一次一密的密钥永远不要使用超过一次
look at some examples where this comes up
in practice. It's a very common mistake to
我们看几个实际当中运用这个的例子 一个常见的错误
use the stream cipher key, or a one time
pad key more than once. Now, let me show
是多次使用流密码密钥或一次一密密钥
you some examples where this comes up. So
you know to avoid these mistakes, when you
我给你们展示几个出现这种错误的例子，从而让你避免在自己建造的系统中不犯这些错误
build your own systems. The first example
is a historic example. At the beginning of
第一个例子是史上著名例子 在20世纪40年代初期
the 1940s, where the Russians actually
used a one time pad to encrypt various
苏联人使用了一次一密加密了多个
mesages. Unfortunately, the pads that they
were using were generated by a human by
信息 很不幸 使用的密码序列是由人们掷骰子产生的
throwing dice. And so, you know, the human
would throw these dice, and write down the
所以 你应该知道 人们掷骰子并记录下结果
results of these throws. And the collected
throws would then form the pads that were
然后收集到的结果就被用作加密的密码本
used for encryption. Now, because it was
kind of laborious for them to generate
而生成这种密码本需要大量的劳动力
these pads, it seems wasteful to use the
pads to encrypt just one message. So the
用它只加密一条信息就显得很浪费
ended up using these pads to encrypt
multiple messages. And US intelligence was
所以最后用这些密码本来加密多条信息 美国情报机关
actually able to intercept these two time
pads. These ciphertexts that were
当时自然可以截获这些二次密码本 这些密文是由
encrypted using the same pad, applied to
different messages. And it turns out, over
不同的明文，使用相同密码本生成的。所以结果是
a period of several years, they were able
to decrypt something like 3,000 plain
经过几年，他们就能够解密约3000条明文
texts just by intercepting these ciphertexts.
The project is called Project Venona
仅凭截获密文 这个计划叫做Venona计划
It's actually a fascinating
of cryptanalysis, just because the two
这是密码分析中很精彩的一幕，仅仅因为二次
time pad is insecure. More importantly, I
want to talk about more recent examples
密码本是不安全的 更重要的 我想讲一些近代的例子
that come up in networking protocols, so
let me give you an example from Windows NT,
这些例子是在网络协议中发现的 来看一个来源于Windows NT的例子
in a product called the,
point-to-point transfer protocol. This is
这个例子是在点到点传输协议中发现的
a protocol for a client wishing to
communicate securely with a server. The
这个协议是为想与服务器安全通信的客户设计的
client and the server both share a secret
key here, and they both send messages to
客户端和服务端共享同一个密钥 并相互通信
one another. So, here, we'll denote the
messages from the client by m1. So, the
这里，我们将客户端发送的明文信息称作m1
client sends a message, the server
responds, the client sends a message, the
客户端发送信息，服务器端应答，客户端发送消息，服务器端应答
server responds, the client sends a
message, the server responds, and so on
客户端发送消息，服务端应答等等
and so forth. Now, the way PPTP works is,
basically, the entire interaction, from
PPTP协议的工作原理是将双方进行整个互动
the client to the server, is considered as
one stream. In other words, what happens
从客户端到服务器端 当作一个流。换句话说
is, the messages m1, and m2 and m3, are
kind of viewed as one long stream.
这里的消息m1，m2，m3被视作一个长流
Here, these two parallel lines means
concatenation. So, essentially, we're
这里双平行线表示串结。本质上
concatenating all the messages from the
client to the server into one long stream.
我们将从客户端到服务器端的信息全部串结成一个长流
And all that stream is encrypted using the
stream cipher with key K. So that's
整个长流使用密钥K来加密 整个过程
perfectly fine. I mean, there's nothing
wrong with that. This messages are
非常好，并没有错误 这些消息被
encrypted, are treated as one long stream,
and they're all encrypted using the same
加密 并且被看做一个长流，并且它们使用相同的密钥来加密
key. The problem is, the same thing is
happening also on the server side. In
问题在于，服务器端也正发生同样的事情
other words, all the messages from the
server are also treated as one long
换句话说，从服务端发出的消息也被看作成一个长流
stream. So here, they're all concatenated
together. And encrypted using,
所以，它们都被串接起来
unfortunately, the same pseudo-random
seed, in other words, using the same
很不幸，加密使用了相同的伪随机种子 换句话说
stream cipher key. So basically what's
happening here is you see an effect that
也就是使用了相同的流密钥。所以你应该想到这里发生一个现象是
the two time pad is taking place where the
set of messages from the client is
二次密码本现象 而这个现象是由一组从客户端来的消息
encrypted using the same one time pad as a
set of messages from the server. The
与一组从服务端来的消息正在使用相同的密码本进行加密而产生的。
lesson here is that you should never use
the same key to encrypt traffic in both
这里的教训是永远不要使用相同的密钥加密两个方向的流量
directions. In fact, what you need to do
is have one key for interaction between
事实上，你需要的是一个密钥加密
the client and the server and one key for
interaction between the server and the
从客户端到服务端的通信，以及另一个密钥加密服务器到客户端的通信。
client. The way I like to write this is
really that the shared key k really is a
我喜欢将这种密钥写成其实是一对密钥的共享密钥k。
pair of keys. One key is used to encrypt
messages from server to client, and one
一个密钥加密从服务器到客户端的消息
key is used to encrypt messages from
client to server. So these are two
另一个加密客户端到服务端的消息 所以有两个
separate keys that are used, and both
sides, of course, know this key. So both
分开的密钥可供使用 当然双方都知道这对密钥
sides have this pair of keys, okay? and
they can both encrypt. So one is used to
所以双方都有这对密钥，对吧？双方都可以进行加密 所以一个用来
encrypt messages in one direction and one
is used to encrypt messages in the other
加密一个方向，另一个用来加密另一个方向。
direction. So another important example of
the two time pad comes up in Wi-Fi
另一个有二次密码本现象的例子是在WI-FI通信中
communication, particularity in the 80211B
protocol. So all of you I'm sure know that
特别是在802.11b的协议中 我相信你们都知道
the 80211 contains an encryption layer and
the original encryption layer was called
802.11包含了一层加密层 最初的加密层叫做WEP
WEP and WEP fortunately for us is actually
a very badly designed protocol so that I
WEP对我们来说实际上是一个设计很糟糕的协议 所以我可以
can always use it as an example of how not
to do things. There are many, many
总是把它拿来当作反面教材
mistakes inside of WEP and here I want to
use it as an example of how the two time
WEP中有很多很多的错误 这里我举产生一个二次密码本现象的例子
pad came about. So let me explain how WEP
works. So in WEP, there's a client and,
先解释一下WEP的工作原理 在WEP中，有一个客户端
and access point. Here's the client,
here's the access point. They both share a
和一个接入点 这是客户端 这是接入点 它们共享
密钥K，然后，当它们想相互通信时
secret key K. And then, when they wanna
transmit a message to one another. Say
假设它们相互传递帧。（帧：一种数据报文） 比如说
these are frames, that they
transmit to one another. Let's say the
客户端想发送一个包含明文M的帧给接入点
client wants to send a frame containing
the plain text M to the access point, what
他首先要做的就是附加校验在明文上
he would do is first of all he appends
some sort of check sum to this plain text.
这里这个校验和并不重要，重要的是接下来这个新的连接（明文+校检）
The check sum is not important at this
point, what is important is then this new
需要用流密码加密 这个流密码密钥是
concatenation gets encrypted using a stream
cypher where the stream cypher key is this
这个IV值和一个长期密钥k的串接 这个IV值为24比特字符串。
concatenation of a value IV and a long
term key K. So this IV is a 24 bit string.
好，这个IV是一个24比特字符串，你可以想到它是以0开始
Okay, this IV is a 24 bit string, and you
can imagine that it starts from zero and
它可能是一个以一包加一的方式计数增量的计数器。
perhaps it's a counter that counts
increments by one for every packet. The
他们这样做的原因是WEP的设计者们知道在流密码中
reason they did this was the designers of
Wep realized that in a stream cypher, the
一个密钥只能加密一个明文信息
key is only supposed to be used to encrypt
one message. So they said well, let's go
所以他们就每帧使用不同的密钥，它们改变密钥的方法就是
ahead and change the key after every
frame. And the way they changed the key
在密钥前面加上IV 你或许会注意到这个IV的改变
essentially was by prepending this IV to
it. And you notice this I-V changes on
在每个数据包中 所以将每个数据包的IV加一 所以IV直接附加密文前面
every packet. So it increments by one on
every packet. And the IV, then, is sent
与密文一起被发送 接收方也知道密钥k
in the clear along with the cipher text.
So the recipient knows the key K. He knows
也知道IV。就能通过串接IV和K重新推出PRG
what the I-V is. He can re-derive the PRG
of IV concatenating  K. And then decrypts
然后就能解密密文，还原明文M了。现在问题在于
the cipher text to recover the original
message M. Now the problem with this
IV只有24比特的长度，也就是说2的24次方
of course is the IV is only 24 bits long.
Which means that there are only two to the
可能的IV，也就是说，经过1600万帧的传输后
24 possible IV's. Which means that after
sixteen million frames are transmitted.
IV又要重0开始循环了，每经过1600万帧循环一次
Essentially the IV has to cycle. And once
it cycles after 16 million frames.
这就有了两次密码本，同样的IV被用来加密两个不同的信息
Essentially we get a two time pad. The
same IV will be used to encrypt two
密钥k的长度不变 它是一个长期的密钥 最终
different messages. The key K never changes.
It's a long term key. And as a result,
相同的密钥，即IV串接K会被用来加密两个不同的帧
that same key, namely the IV concatenated K
would be used to encrypt two different
然后攻击者可以解出两个帧的原文来
frames, and the attacker can then figure
out the plain text of both frames. So
这是一个问题，更严重的问题是在很多802.11网卡上
that's one problem. And the worst problem
is in fact that on many 80211 cards, if
如果你重启网卡 IV会被重置为0 于是
you powercycle the card, the IV will reset
back to zero. And as a result, everytime
每次重新启动网卡，加密下次有效负载，
you powercycle the card, essentially
you'll be encrypting the next payload
用的都是0和密钥K的串接 所以每次重启网卡后，你都要使用0串接k
using zero concatenated K  So after every
powercycle, you'll be using the zero
来加密许多许多相同数据包
concatenated K key to encrypt many, many,
many times the same packets. So you see
所以在WEP中，只要IV被重置 同样的密码本就会用来加密许多不同的信息
how in WEP, the same pad could be used to
encrypt many different messages as soon as
我们无法防止重启后IV被重置的现象
the IV is repeated. There is nothing to
prevent the IV from repeating after a
或者1600万帧后归零，1600万帧在忙碌的网络中并不算多
powercycle. Or am repeating after every
sixteen million frames which isn't that
所以当我们在讨论WEP时，我会提到WEP的
many frames in a busy network. So while we
are talking about WEP. I want to mention
另一个错误 这个确实是一个很严重的错误
one more mistake that was done in WEP.
This is a pretty significant mistake and
我们来看如何更好的设计它。大家都注意到WEP的设计者
let's see how we might design it better.
So you notice that the designers of WEP
本质上想为每个数据包使用不同的密钥 所以每个帧
basically wanted to use a different key
for every packet. Okay. So every frame is
使用不同的密钥加密，即不同的IV和k串接
encrypted using a different key
is concatonation of IV and K.
很遗憾，它们没有随机选取密钥
Unfortunately. They didn't randomize the
keys and the keys are actually, if you
如果单看第一帧的密钥，它一定是
look at the key for frame number one,
well, you know, it will be this
1与k的串接 当然 这个IV不能填满24比特
concatenation of one and k. it wouldn't fill this 24 bits. Then the key for frame
第二帧的密钥是2和k的串接，第三帧的密钥是
number two is the concatenation of two and
k. The key for frame number three is the
3与k的串接 所以这些密钥之间非常接近
concatenation of three and k. So the keys
are very closely related to one another.
我还应该提到这些密钥本身可以是104比特 因此
And I should probably mention also that
these keys themselves can be 104 bits so
PRG生成密钥实际上是104+24=128比特
that the resulting PRG key is actually
104 plus 24 bytes which is 128 bytes.
很遗憾这些密钥之间太过相近 它们并不是
Unfortunately these keys are very much
related to one another. These are not
随机密钥 大家注意到它们都有相同的104字节的后缀
random keys. You notice they all have the
same suffix of 104 bytes. And it turns out
事实上WEP里的伪随机密钥并没有设计的那么安全
the pseudo-random generator used in Wep is
not designed to be secure when you use
因为你使用了相近的密钥 换句话说 大部分密钥
related keys that are so closely related.
In other words, the majority of these keys
之间是一样的 事实上 对于WEP中使用的PRG叫做RC4
are basically the same. And in fact, for
the PRG that's used in WEP. That PRG is
我们将在下一节中了解更多
called, RSC four. We'll talk about that
more in the next segment. It turns out
在2001年由Fluhrer，Mantin，Shamir三人发现了一个攻击
there's an attack. It was discovered by
Fluhrer, Mantin and Shamir
证实经过10的6次方，约100万帧后
back in 2001, that shows that after about
ten to the six of, after about a million
你就可以还原密钥了 所以这是一个很严重的
frames. You can recover the secret key.
Can recover key. So, this is kind of a
攻击，要想破译只需监听一百万帧就可以了
disastrous attack that says essentially
all you have to do is listen to a million
刚才说过，这些帧全部由一个共同种子生成
frames. These frames basically. As we said
they're all generated from a very common
也就是说104位的种子序列全部一样
seed, namely a 104 bits of these seeds are
all the same. The fact that they've used
这足以还原出密钥了
such closely related keys is enough to
actually recover the original key. And it
实际上经过2001年的攻击，更好的攻击方案开始出现
turns out even after the 2001 attack,
better attacks have come out that show
证明了这种密钥关联是灾难性的 事实上
that these related keys are very much
disastrous and in fact these days
最近又发现4万帧就足以破解 因此
something like 40,000 frames are
sufficient. And so that, within a matter
在几分钟内你就可以还原任何WEP网络中使用的密钥了
of minutes, you can actually recover the
secret key in any WEP network. So
所以WEP基于下面两个原因无法提供任何的安全性。第一
WEP provides no security at all
for two reasons. First of all, it can
它像二次密码本一样脆弱，但是更重要的是
resolve into the two time pad. But more
significantly, because these keys are so
因为这些密钥之间的紧密关联，仅窃听少量密文就可以还原密钥
closely related, it's actually possible to
recover the key by watching just a few
顺便说下，当我们对加密机制里的步骤进行安全分析时 更好地了解这个性质
cipher texts. And by the way, we'll see
that well, when we do a security analysis
在下几节里，我们会开始讨论如何分析
of these steps of constructions. In a few
segments, we'll start talking about how to
加密机制里的步骤 我们会发现当我们使用这样紧密关联的密钥时
analyze these steps of constructions.
We'll see that when we have related keys
事实上 会导致我们安全分析的失败 我们无法得到
like this, in fact, our security analysis
will fail. We won't be able to get the
可以被通过的证据 所以WEP的设计者们应当怎么办？
proof to go through. So one could ask what
should the designers of a WEP should have
一个方法是对帧进行处理，M1，
done, instead? Well, one approach is to
basically treat the frames, you know M1,
M2，M3等 每一帧都是由客户端分开发向服务端
M2, M3. Each, each one is a separate frame
transmitter from the client to the server.
也可以把它们当作长流处理 然后进行异或操作
He could have treated them as one
long stream, and then XOR them
使用伪随机数发生器产生长流
potentially. Using the pseudo random
generator as one long stream. So the first
密码本的第一节用来加密M1
segment of the pad would have been used to
encrypt M1. The second
密码本的第二节用来加密M2
segment of the pad would have been used to
encrypt M2. The third segment
密码本的第三节用来加密M3.等等
of the pad would have been used to encrypt
M3. And so on and so forth.
所以设计者们不必对每一帧都改变密钥
So they basically could never have had to
change the key because the entire
因为整个会话应被视作长流 但是他们为每一帧选出不同的密钥
interaction is viewed as one long stream.
But they chose to have a different key for
所以如果你想这么做，有更好的方法
every frame. So if you want to do that, a
better way to do that is, rather than
不是轻微改变IV，即轻微改变PRG的密钥前缀
slightly modifying this IV that just
slightly modifies the prefix of the key,
更好的办法是再次使用PRG 所以本质上
of the PRG key. A better way to do that is
to use a PRG again. So essentially, what
你能做的是获得一个长期密钥 然后把长期密钥输入到
you could do is you will take your long
term key. And then feed that directly
PRG里 这样我们就得到了一个长流 而且它看起来是随机的
through a PRG. So now we get a long stream
of bits that look essentially random.
然后可以使用最初密码本的部分，第一段可以当作密钥
And then the initial segment could be
used, the first segment could be used as
来加密第一帧。第二段当作密钥
the key, or frame number one. And then the
second segment would be used as the key
来加密第二帧等等
for, you know, key for frame number two.
And so on and so forth. The third segment
第三段加密第三帧等等 所以这样做比较好的方面是
would be used to encrypt frame #three and
so on and so forth, okay? So the nice
每一帧都有一个伪随机密钥了
thing about this is now, essentially, by
doing this, each frame has a pseudo-random
这些密钥之间没有关系了，它们看起来像是随机密钥
key. These keys, now, have no relation to
one another. They look like random keys.
所以，如果PRG对于任意种子序列是安全的，那它对这个输入也是安全的
And as a result, if the PRG is secure for
random seeds, it was also be secure on this
因为密钥看起来相互之间是独立的
input. Because these keys essentially look
as though they're independent of one
当我们讨论完这些加密机制后 再来做正式的分析
another. We'll see how to do this analysis
formally once we talk about these types of
既然二次密码本的攻击在实践中很容易碰到，
constructions. Since this two-time pad
attack comes up so often in practice, it's
毕竟这也是一个常见错误，我想通过举出另一个的例子让大家避免犯错
such a common mistake, I want to give one
more example where it comes up so you know
最后一个例子是在磁盘加密的环境下讨论的
how to avoid it. The last example I want
to give is in the context of disk
想象我们有一个文件 也许这个文件开头是
encryption. So imagine we have a certain
file and maybe the file begins with, you
“给Bob的话”，后面跟着文件内容
know, the words to Bob. And then the
contents of the file follows.
when this is
当把文件存在磁盘上时 假设这个是磁盘
stored on disk of course the file is gonna
get so here(好像有错，听不出来) we have our disk here, the
文件被分块放置，对于每一块，
file is going to get broken into blocks.
And each block will be, you know, when we
当我们把分块存放在硬盘上时 就会对其加密
actually store this on a disk, you know,
things will be encrypted. You know, so
那么“给Bob的话”就会放到第一块，余下的内容将
maybe to Bob will go into the first block
and then the rest of the content will go
放在剩下的分块里 当然这全部被加密了
into the remaining blocks. But of course
this is all incrypted so I'll kind of use
我用这些红线来表示被它们被加密了
these lines here to denote the fact that
this is encrypted. And an attacker looking
一个攻击者可以看到看硬盘却不知道文件内容是什么 那么现在假设
at the disk has no idea what the contents
of the message is. But now suppose that at
假设经过一段时间后，用户做出修改，基本上启动了编辑器
a later time, user goes ahead and
modifies, basically fires up the editor.
它修改了文件 现在不是“给Bob” 而是“给Eve”
It modifies the file, so now instead of
saying to Bob, it says to Eve. And nothing
文件其余内容不改变，仅改变这个地方
else changes in the file, that's the only
change that was made. When the user then
当用户将修改保存到硬盘，它将再次加密一遍
saves this modified file to disk,
basically he's gonna re encrypt it again.
所以相同的事情又发生了一遍，这个文件又被分成了几块
And so the same thing is gonna happen. The
file is gonna get broken into blocks. You
现在这个文件是发给Eve，所有内容均被加密
know, now the file's gonna say to Eve. And
everything, of course, is gonna be
所以我又要用这些线表示加密，现在有攻击者正在浏览磁盘
encrypted. So again, I'll, put these lines
here. Now an attacker looking at the disc,
并得到了文件编辑前的快照 之后又继续观察编辑后的磁盘
taking a snapshot of the disc before the
edits. And then looking again at the disc
他会发现改变的地方仅仅是
after the edits. What he will see is that
the only thing that changed is this little
这一小段不一样，其他地方都一模一样
segment here. That's now different.
Everything else looks exactly the same. So
即使攻击者不知道文件是如何修改的
the attacker, even though he doesn't know
what actually happened to the file within
他却知道修改的确切位置
the file or what changed, he knows exactly
the location where the edits took place.
事实上，一次一密或密码流一次加密一比特
And so the fact that the one-time path or
a stream cypher encrypts one bit at a time
意味着如果一处发生改变，很容易立刻发现变化的位置
means that if one change takes place, then
it's very easy to tell where that change
这就泄露了攻击者不应该知道的信息
occurred instantly. That leaks information
that the attacker shouldn't actually
理想情况下，即使文件有一点改动
learn. Ideally you'd like to say that even
if the file changed just a little bit.
整个文件就应该被改变 或者至少这些分块的内容会有所改变
Entire contents of the file should change.
Or maybe at least the entire contents of
攻击者甚至知道改变发生在哪一分块
the blocks should change. Here you can see
the attacker even knows within the block
事实上正因如此，通常
where the change was actually made, okay.
So in fact, because of this, it's usually
磁盘加密使用流密码不是一个好方法，本质上
a bad idea to use stream cyphers for disk
encryption. And essentially this is
这是二次密码本攻击的又一个例子 因为相同的密码本被用来加密
another example of a two-time pad attack
because the same pad is used to encrypt
两条不同的信息 上面与下面的信息 虽然非常相似 但它们是两条
two different messages. This, they happen
to be very similar, but nevertheless these
不同的信息，攻击者可以知道什么改变了
are two different messages, and the
attacker can learn what the change was and
最终他还可能知道改变的内容是什么
in fact he might be able to even learn
what the actual changed words were, as a
所以这里的教训是，我们需要做些不同的东西来
result of this. Okay, so the lesson here
is generally we need to do something
执行磁盘加密 在后面的章节中我们再来讨论磁盘加密
different for disk encryption. We'll talk
about what to do for disk encryption in a
但是一般来说 一次一密不是用来加密磁盘块的好方法
later segment, but essentially the
one-time pad is generally not a good idea
那么再总结一下二次密码本攻击
for encrypting blocks on disks. So just
again to summarize the two-time pad
我希望我已说服你
attack, we saw that you're supposed, I
hope I've convinced you that you're never
千万不要重复使用流密码密钥超过一次 即使
ever, ever supposed to use a stream cypher
key more than once. Even though there are
有这种情况可能会发生的自然环境，你也需要小心并确保
natural settings where that might happen,
you have to take care and make sure that
不会重复使用同样的密钥超过一 因此对网络流量来说
you're not using the same key more than
once. So for network traffic typically
你需要做的是，每次会话都有对应的密钥
what you're supposed to do is every
session would have its own key. Within the
会话内从客户端到服务端的信息可以视作一个完整流
session the message from the client and
the server look as one complete stream. It
并使用一个密钥加密该信息 从服务器端到客户端的消息也
would be encrypted using one key.  the
messages from the server to the client
可视作一个流 并用不同的密钥加密该流
would be treated as one stream and
encrypted using a different key. And then
然后对于磁盘加密 一般不使用流密码 因为每当
for disc encryption typically would not
use a stream cypher because. As changes
对文件的修改 流密码算法会泄露文件内容
are made to the file, he would be leaking
information about the contents of the
好，我们总结完了二次密码本的讨论内容
file. Okay, so that concludes our brief
discussion of the two time pad.
下面我们来谈一个攻击，事实上，一次一密和流密码
Next attack I want to mention. Is a fact
that the one time path and stream cyphers
并不提供完整性保护，他们所做的仅仅是在只使用密钥一次的情况下提供
in general provide no integrity at all.
All they do is they try to provide
机密性 他们根本不提供完整性
confidentiality when the key's only used
once. They provide no integrity at all but
更糟糕的是 这两种加密实际上很容易修改密文
even worse than that it's actually very
easy to modify cypher texts and have known
并且对通信原文造成显著影响，让我来解释一下
effects on the corresponding plain text.
So let me explain what I mean by that.
顺便说下，这个性质叫柔韧性（易受外界影响） 待会会看到
This property, by the way, is called
malleability, and we'll see what I mean by
设想有明文Ｍ被加密
that in just a second. So imagine we have
some message M that gets encrypted. So,
使用流密码加密 密文当然应该是
here, it gets encrypted using a stream
cipher. And the cipher text, of course, is
由Ｍ异或密钥ｋ得来，现在一攻击者截取密文
then gonna be, M XOR a K. Now an
attacker intercepts the cypher text. Well,
只有密文他当然不知道原明文是怎么样的 不过除了窃听以外
that doesn't tell him what's, what the
plain text is but what he can do is now
攻击者还可以积极篡改密文
beyond eavesdropping he can actually
become an active attacker and modify the
当我说篡改密文时 我们假设他
cypher text. So when I say modify the
cypher text let's suppose that he
将密文和一特定值ｐ异或，ｐ称作子置换密钥
XOR the cypher text with a certain
value P. Whats called a sub-permutation key.
这样密文就成了ｍ异或ｋ异或ｐ
Well, the resulting cipher text then
becomes M XOR K, XOR P. So now I'll
我问你们，当我们解密时，我们能够解密得到什么
ask you, when we decrypt the cipher text,
what is it going to decrypt to? Well I
大家应该都了解异或操作，解密后为ｍ异或ｐ
hope everybody sees manipulating the XORs
Basically the decryption becomes M XOR P
注意到异或密码本ｐ后 攻击者就会
So you notice that by XOR with this pad P, the attacker was able to
对明文造成特定的影响 所以一句话说就是
have a very specific effect on the
resulting plain text. Okay. So a summary
你可以修改密文，但这些修改将不会被检测出来
is basically you can modify the cypher
text. These modifications are undetected.
更糟糕的是，它们无法检测，它们对还原的明文有特定影响
But even worse than undetected, they
have a very specific impact on the
也就是说 不管你拿什么跟密文异或
resulting plain text. Namely whatever you
XOR the cipher text with is going to have
都会对明文产生影响 为了看出什么地方是危险的
that exact effect on the plain text. So to
see where this can be dangerous, let's
我们来看一个特别的例子，假设用户发送了一分Email
look at a particular example. Suppose the
user sends an email that starts with the
邮件以“来自Bob”开头，攻击者截获通信密文
words from Bob. In the attacker
intercepts the corresponding cypher text.
他不知道密文是什么 但为说明方便我们假设
He doesn't know what the cypher text is
but let's just for the sake of it let's
他知道这信来自Ｂｏｂ
pretend that he actually knows that this
message is actually from Bob. What he
他想修改密文，让明文变得看起来像来自于另外一个人
wants to do is he wants to modify the
ciphertext so that the plain text would
比如说，他想让这封信看起来
now look like it came from somebody else.
Say, he wants to make it look like this
好像是从Alice发来的 攻击者只有密文 但他能做的是
message actually came from Alice. All he
has is the ciphertext. Well, what he can
不过他可以异或特定的三个字母 我们等会会看到
do is he can XOR with a certain
three characters. We'll see
三个字母是哪三个字母 因此
what those three characters are in just a
second. And such that the resulting
密文就变成从Eve发来的 所以
ciphertext is actually an encryption of
the message from Eve. And so that now when
等用户解密时，突然他会认为 这封信来自Eve
the user decrypts that. All of a sudden
he'll see, Hey, this message is from Eve.
虽然是错的 但他认为信来自Eve而不是Bob 并且这可能会导致接下来
It's not, he'll think this message is from
Eve, not from Bob. And that might cause
不好事情的发生 所以攻击者 即使
you know, the wrong thing to take place.
So here the attacker, even though he
不能自己创造密文声称信件来自Eve 通过修改
himself could not have created a cypher
text that says from Eve, by modifying an
已有的密文 瞬间他也可以创造密文 当然一般情况下 除非
existing cypher text all of a sudden he
was able to make the cypher text that he
截取窃听密文，否则他也不能达到目的 所以
could not have done without intercepting
at least one cypher text. So again by
通过截获一段密文，修改一下，就可以使其看起来是来自Eve
intercepting one cypher text he was able
to change it so not it looks like it's
而不是Bob，特别地，我们来看这三个字母是什么
from Eve, rather than from Bob. So just to
be specific, let's look what these three
我们看单词Bob，我用ASCII表示
characters need to be, so let's look at
the word Bob. And I'm going to write it in
Bob相当于ASCII码的16进制42，6F和62
askee. So Bob in askee corresponds to 42
hex six f hex and 62 hex. So little b is
b被编码成62，o被编码成6F，单词Eve被编码成45、76
encoded as 62, little o is encoded as six
f. The word eve is encoded as 45 hex, 76
65，当我异或这两个词时，我以字符串的形式异或
hex, and 65 hex. Now when I XOR these
two words, I'm literally going to x over
Bob异或Eve，不难看出 得到的是
them as bit strings. So Bob XOR eve,
it's not difficult to see that what I get
三个字符07，19，07 所以这三个字符应该是什么呢
are the three characters zero, seven.
Nineteen and 07. So really what these
就是简单的字符07，19，07
three characters here are going to be. Are
simply 07, nineteen, and 07. And by
能过在密文正确的位置异或这三个字母
XORing these three characters at the
right positions into the cipher text, the
攻击者可以将密文改成来自Eve而不是Bob
attacker was able to change the cipher
text to look like it came from Eve rather
这就是一个对密文造成可预测影响的例子
than from Bob. So this is an example
where having a predictable impact on the
这个影响确实能造成一些问题 而这个属性就
cipher text can actually cause quite a bit
of problems. And this is this property
叫做柔韧性（容易被改变） 我们说一次一密是具柔韧性的 是因为
called malleability. And we say that the
one time pad is malleable because it's
密文很容易推算 并将特定改变应用到
very easy to compute in cipher texts, and
make prescribed changes to the
明文上 为了防止这点 我将
corresponding plain text. So to prevent
all this, I'm gonna do that, actually, in
花两三讲的时间 来为大家展示如何为加密机制增加完整性
two or three lectures. And we're gonna
basically show how to add integrity to
我希望大家可以记住
encryption mechanisms in general. But
right now I want you to remember that the
一次一密本身是没有完整性保护的
one time pad by itself has no integrity
and is completely insecure against
并且针对可修改密文的攻击者来说是完全不安全的
attackers that actually modify the cipher
texts.